Vignesh Venkatraman

Nationality: Indian Date of birth: 21/06/1991 Gender: Male Phone number: (+353) 892337851

Email address: vigneshvenkat_21@live.com | LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/vignesh-venkatraman-33677657/

• Home: 15 Woodlawn Grove, Cork Road, X91 YFT6 Waterford (Ireland)

ABOUT ME

A passionate product developer with over ten years of experience specialised in research & development of advanced IT products used by small and medium scale enterprises. I always have the urge to learn latest technologies which are currently used by world-class tech companies and implement them within our solutions.

VISA STATUS: STAMP 1

TECHNOLOGIES OF INTEREST: React, Vue, Node, JavaScript, TypeScript, Bootstrap.

WORK EXPERIENCE

IT PROJECT MANAGER - TECH & TRANSFORMATION

Waterford Insulation [06/02/2024 - Current]

City: Waterford | Country: Ireland

WATERFORD INSULATION

Waterford Insulation is a leading provider of cavity wall insulation, both internal and external wall insulation, spray foam insulation, attic & acoustic insulation, fire proofing, plumbing, renewable technology services, wall & roof ventilation.

RESPONSIBILITIES HELD

- 1. Lead a team of developers to work oon projects and deliver them on time.
- 2. Work with stakeholders to understand their IT needs and define project scope for software implementations.
- 3. Develop project plans with timelines, milestones, budgets, and resource allocation.
- 4. Conduct risk assessments and mitigation strategies.
- 5. Manage and oversee the project execution according to the plan, ensuring tasks are completed on time and within budget.
- 6. Monitor project progress, identify and address any roadblocks or delays, and implement corrective actions.
- 7. Ensure successful project completion by testing, documenting, and training users on new systems or processes.
- 8. Develop handover documentation for future reference and maintenance.
- 9. Evaluate project outcomes and collect feedback for continuous improvement.

TECHNOLOGIES USED: React, Redux, Vue, Node, JavaScript, TypeScript.

TECHNICAL LEAD

Zoho Corporation Private Limited [20/03/2019 – 09/02/2022]

City: Chennai | Country: India

ZOHO CRM-Enterprise Business Solutions

Zoho CRM is an on-demand, SaaS-based customer relationship management (CRM) software solution designed to manage sales, marketing, contacts, customer support, and other business functions in a single cohesive platform.

RESPONSIBILITIES HELD

- 1. Performed as a Technical Lead by leading my development team to produce quality work.
- 2. Developed widgets using top Javascript and CSS frameworks to implement client's feature requests.
- 3. Responsible for on-boarding of new hires, teaching organization's development process and setting them goals.
- 4. Captured business requirements and designed plans on implementing client's business model with our Zoho CRM.
- 5. Explore new technologies available and employ them in our product to improve efficiency.

TECHNOLOGIES USED: React, Redux, Vue, Node, Bootstrap, JavaScript, TypeScript, Webpack, AWS.

MEMBER TECHNICAL STAFF

Zoho Corporation Private Limited [14/02/2015 – 19/03/2019]

City: Chennai | Country: India

ZOHO VAULT

An online password manager for individuals and teams which stores passwords and other confidential data in a centralized encrypted vault for secure access and management.

RESPONSIBILITIES HELD

- 1. Revamped our product's UI using an internally developed Javascript Framework.
- 2. Developed a tool in Python language to perform encryption and decryption of the saved passwords.
- 3. Developed features such as automatic change password for websites, form filling, WebExtensions, etc.
- 4. Overall in-charge of browser extensions for platforms like Google Chrome, Mozilla Firefox, Microsoft Edge & Opera.
- 5. Responsible for on-boarding of new hires, teaching the organization's development process and setting them goals.

TECHNOLOGIES USED: React, Redux, Vue, Node, JavaScript, Java, Webpack, AWS, MySQL, REST API.

ENGINEER TRAINEE

Zoho Corporation Private Limited [02/02/2014 – 13/02/2015]

City: Chennai | Country: India

MANAGEENGINE SECURITY MANAGER PLUS

A network security scanner that proactively reports on network vulnerabilities and helps to remediate them and ensure compliance.

RESPONSIBILITIES HELD

- 1. Developed feature enhancements based on the list of customer promises.
- 2. Handled mission critical and emergency situations as part of the technical support team.
- 3. Updated the vulnerability database periodically by adding latest vulnerabilities revealed by international regulatory bodies like Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures, National Institute of Science and Technology, etc.
- 4. Updated the patch database by adding the patches released for the respective vulnerabilities exposed on products developed by famous brands like Adobe, Google, Microsoft, etc.
- 5. Delivered hot-fixes as and when required.

TECHNOLOGIES USED: Java, JavaScript, JQuery, HTML, CSS, Postgres, JSP.

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Msc in Cybersecurity

National College of Ireland [24/01/2022 - 25/01/2023]

City: Dublin | Country: Ireland

DIGITAL SKILLS

React / Vue / Node / Redux / Webpack / ExpressJS / JavaScript / TypeScript / Bootstrap / MongoDB / MySQL / Python / Django / AWS

PROJECTS

[16/06/2022 - 07/07/2022]

Gaelikart Gaelikart is an E-Commerce site which sells Irish alcoholic beverages online. This is one of the projects i developed for the "Secure Programming for Web" module in our Master's degree.

[10/09/2022 – 15/12/2022]

Adapting Argon2 Hashing Algorithm for a Strong Zero Knowledge Password Proof Authentication Research work attempted to employ "Zero Knowledge Protocol" and "Argon2 hashing" with a goal to develop a secure NodeJS password authentication system.